Preliminary Inventory of the Robert Charlwood Richardson papers, 1917-1954
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert Charlwood Richardson, Jr. papers
1917-1954
68029
Hoover Institution Archives
74 manuscript boxes (30.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, bulletins, directives, maps, and photographs relating to American military operations in the Pacific Theater during World War II and the American Expeditionary Forces in World War I.
Richardson, Robert C. (Robert Charlwood)
Access
Boxes 11A, 38, 41-42, 47, 52, 55-57, 61, 63-64 and 73-74 are open for research. All others may not be used without permission of the Archivist. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for more information.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1968.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Delos Carleton Emmons papers, Hoover Institution Archives William Edward Hammer processed volume, Hoover Institution Archives Raymond B. Jordan collection, Hoover Institution Archives Henry J. Muller, Jr. papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1882 Born, Charleston, South Carolina
1900-1904 Cadet, United States Military Academy at West Point (USMA)
Circa 1904-1905 Served in the 14th Calvary Regiment during the Philippine–American War
1905 Wounded in action at Cotta Usap
1906-1911 Assistant instructor of modern languages, United States Military Academy at West Point (USMA)
1914-1916 Assistant professor of English, United States Military Academy at West Point (USMA)
1917 Aide to Major General T. H. Barry Author, West Point: An Intimate Picture of the National Military Academy
1918-1919 Liaison officer, American Expeditionary Forces
1919 Joined Morale Division, War Plans Division, War Department General Staff, Washington DC
1920-1923 Assistant to assistant chief of staff for operations, Headquarters, Philippine Department, Manila
1924-1926 Attended Ecole Supérieure de Guerre, Paris
1926-1928 Military attaché, Rome, Italy
1929-1933 Commandant of cadets, United States Military Academy at West Point (USMA)
1933 Attended Army War College, Washington
1938 Given command of the 2nd Cavalry Brigade at Fort Bliss, Texas
1940-1941 Commanded the 1st Calvary Division Fort Bliss, Texas
1941 Director, Bureau of Public Relations, War Department
1943- Military governor of Hawaii Commanding general of U.S. Army forces in the Pacific Ocean area Commanding general of the Hawaiian Department
1954 Died Posthumously promoted to general
Scope and Contents of Collection
The papers document the military career of General Robert Charlwood Richardson, Jr., who served in World War I and World War II. Materials include correspondence, memoranda, bulletins, directives, maps, and photographs relating to American military operations in the Pacific Theater during World War II and the American Expeditionary Forces in World War I.
As an aide to Major General T. H. Barry, Richardson traveled with Barry to Europe in 1917. Since Richardson could speak French, he became a liaison officer for the American Expeditionary Forces during World War I. The collection includes materials related to the American Expeditionary Forces and volumes of information summaries.
During World War II, Richardson became the military governor of Hawaii and the commander of Army personnel in the Pacific. He was present aboard the USS Missouri during Japan's surrender in 1945. The collection contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, and photographs related to Richardson's service, as well as history volumes documenting the United States Armed Forces in the Middle Pacific. Also included are materials concerning martial law in Hawaii and suspension of the right of habeas corpus during Richardson's service as military governor.
Index to Major Groups
37
Biographical file
1-4, 7
World War I
5-6, 8-11
Interwar period
12-57
World War II
63-71
Correspondence
12, 37
Speeches and writings
36, 38, 61-62
Photographs
United States. Army--Officers.; Hawaii.; United States--Armed Forces.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.; World War, 1939-1945--Hawaii.; World War, 1939-1945.
- American Expeditionary Forces, 1917-1919 (Box 1-4)
  Scope and Contents note
  See also: Ecole Supérieure de Guerre, Box 8-9.
  - General, 1917-1919 (Box 1-2)
  - "Summary of Information, Second Section, General Staff, General Headquarters,", 1917 October-1918 October (Box 2-3)
  - "Summary of Air Information, Second Section, General Staff, General Headquarters,", 1918 March-November (Box 3)
  - "Summary of Intelligence, Second Section, General Staff, General Headquarters,", 1918 April-November
  - "Press Review, Second Section, General Staff, General Headquarters,", 1917 December-1919 June (Box 4)
- Philippine Department, 1921-1922 (Box 5-6)
  - "Orders, Bulletins, and Memoranda," volume 1 to 3, 1921-1922 (Box 5-6)
    Prepared by Personnel Division, General Staff (G1), Philippine Department.
  - "Studies, Orders, Bulletins and Other Papers," by Robert C. Richardson, 2 volumes, 1921-1922 (Box 6)
- Military books and pamphlets, 1906-1938 (Box 7, 36, 61)
  Mainly related to World War I.
- Ecole Supérieure de Guerre, Paris, 1911-1934 (Box 8-9)
  Includes materials related to the American Expeditionary Forces.
- "Third Army Command Post Exercises," 6 volumes, 1936 (Box 10-11)
- Central Pacific Command, 1941-1949 (Box 12-23)
  See also: declassified materials in Box 73-74.
  - Joint communications, Central Pacific area, 1942-1945 (Box 12)
    Includes communications, memoranda, speeches, and conference data, as well as "Where Do We Stand?" and "Inauguration Address" by Richardson.
  - Central Pacific combat and status reports, 1942-1945 (Box 12-14)
    Includes reports on Aitutaki, Angaur, Baker, Bora Bora, Efate, Fanning, Makin, Marshall Islands, New Zealand, Nukufetau, Palmyra, Penrhyn (Tongareua), Russell Islands, Tongatabu, Tulagi, Tutuila, Upolu, and Wallis; reports on participation in the Galvanic Operation in the Gilbert Islands and the Kwajalein and Eniwetok Operations; and transcripts of telephone conversations.
  - Military combat reports, 1944-1949 (Box 15-16)
    Includes Richardson's notes on operations in the Gilbert and Marshall Islands.
  - Correspondence and communication files, 1942-1946 (Box 17-20)
    Includes Commanding General, U.S. Army Forces, Pacific Ocean Areas (COMGENPOA) and Commander-In-Chief, Pacific Ocean Areas (CINCPOA) files.
  - Correspondence, memoranda, summaries of meetings, and MacArthur file, 1941-1945 (Box 21)
    Includes correspondence with John McCloy.
  - Orders, reports, memoranda, and subject files, 1942-1946 (Box 22-23)
- Military Governor of Hawaii, 1941-1946 (Box 24-31)
  - "Wartime Security Controls in Hawaii, 1941-1945: A General Historical Survey," part 1 to 8 (Box 24-25, 30)
  - Martial law, 1941-1946 (Box 25-27)
    See also: declassified materials in Box 74.
  - Investigation related to Joseph Petrowski, 1946 (Box 27-28)
  - Habeas corpus cases, 1942-1946 (Box 28-29)
    Includes materials concerning case of Lloyd C. Duncan. See also: declassified materials in Box 74.
  - Civil affairs, 1943-1945 (Box 31)
- World War II administrative and policy documents, correspondence, demobilization file, and personnel in Japan, 1941-1946 (Box 32-33)
- Public Relations Bureau, War Department, 1941, 1945 (Box 34)
  Includes correspondence with Julius Klein discussing the possibility of a motion picture film.
- Saipan incident, Holland Smith/Ralph Smith controversy, 1944, 1948-1949 (Box 35-36)
  See also: declassified materials in Box 73.
- Speeches and writings, 1944-1960 (Box 37)
  Includes first two chapters of Richardson's memoirs, published in the WDBPR veteran's newsletter.
- Biographical file, 1944-1962 (Box 37)
  Includes clippings about Richardson and photograph.
- Photographic portraits of Richardson, February 17, 1942 (Box 38)
- VII Corps, administrative files and photographs, 1941 (Box 38)
  - VII Corps Training photographs (7 files), circa 1941-1943 (Box 38)
    Includes parades, training scenes, airplanes, calvary, and many group photographs. Also includes some Richardson portraits at training areas.
  - Report of the VII Corps Exercises, October 1941 (Box 38)
  - VII Corps reports and correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box 38)
  - Fort Bliss, Texas, housing issues reports and correspondence, 1941 (Box 38)
  - VII Corps training reports for the 81st, 79th, and 73rd divisions, 1943 (Box 38)
  - Western Defense Command report, 1941 (Box 38)
  - VII Corps and Western Defense Command reports, March-April 1942 (Box 38)
    Includes Defense of the Continental U.S. reports
- U.S. Air Force and radar reports and materials, 1944-1955 (Box 39)
  - 1942 (Box 39)
  - Airdrome lists, South Pacific Area, undated (Box 39)
  - Radar in Hawaii, 1943-1945 (Box 39)
  - 7th Air Force Operations, November 1943-January 1944 (Box 39)
    Includes photographs
  - South Pacific Report, 1943 (Box 39)
  - Air Forces Report, 1941 (Box 39)
  - Report from Australian Air Corps, September 1942 (Box 39)
  - Correspondence on Air Commands, August 1943-February 1944 (Box 39)
  - Correspondence on Air Commands, January - May, 1945 (Box 39)
  - Messages regarding Air Force units, July 1945-1946 (Box 39)
- Air Force Manual Revision, 1945 (Box 39)
- History volumes, "United States Army Forces, Middle Pacific and Predecessor Commands,", 1941-1945 (Box 40-57)
  - History of Adjutant General's Office, Artillery Section and Chaplain's Section (Box 40)
  - "History of Chemical Warfare,", undated (Box 41-42)
    - Volume I to III (Box 41)
    - Volume IV to V (Box 42)
  - "History of Engineer Section,", undated (Box 43-44)
    - Volume I to II (Box 43)
    - Volume III to IV (Box 44)
  - "History of an Exchange and Fiscal Section,", 1941-1945 (Box 45)
  - "History of the G-1 Section,", 1941-1945 (Box 46)
  - "History of G-2 Section" and "History of G-4 Section,", 1941-1945 (Box 47)
  - "History of the G-4 Section" and "History of G-5 Section,", 1941-1945 (Box 48)
  - "History of H.Q. Commandant, Appendix," "Office of the Surgeon," and "History of Ordinance Section,", 1941-1945 (Box 49)
  - "History of Provost Marshal's Office,", 1941-1945 (Box 50-52)
  - "History of the G-3 Section" and "Replacement Training Offices,", 1941-1945 (Box 52)
  - "History of Public Relations," "History of Quarter Master," "History of Judge Advocate's Office," and "History of Replacement Sections,", 1941-1945 (Box 53)
  - "History of Signal," "History of Special Service," "History of the Inspector General's Section," and "History of the Transportation Section,", 1941-1945 (Box 54)
  - World War II department histories, undated (Box 55-57)
    - Volume 1 to 5 (Box 55)
    - Volume 6 to 10 (Box 56)
    - Volume 11 to 15 (Box 57)
- Maps, memoranda, and history of Army port and service command, 1943-1947, undated (Box 58)
- World War II correspondence and memoranda, public relations file, Army and Navy relationships file, 1944-1945 (Box 59)
- Correspondence, memoranda, orders, and directives pertaining to Hawaii and the Pacific Ocean and public relations file, 1943-1945 (Box 60, 72)
- Military books and pamphlets, 1917-1938 (Box 61)
- Army Officers' manuals (Box 61)
- "An Army Interlude: Kilauea Military Camp," brochure, circa 1944 (Box 61)
- Signal Corps photographs (Box 61-62)
  - General Richardson's office in Hawaii, undated (Box 61)
    1 album containing 22 prints.
  - General Richardson's residence, Fort Shafter, undated (Box 61)
  - Pearl Harbor and Pacific Islands, World War II, 1944 (Box 61)
    1 album containing 31 prints.
  - Pacific Islands, World War II, 1944-1945 (Box 62)
    1 album.
  - Army University Center, Oahu; Schofield barracks, 1945-1946
  - General World War II photographs, 1944-1945, undated (Box 62)
    Mainly groups of officers and soldiers, some including cars, airplanes, and other machinery. Also includes aerial shots from an airplane.
  - Visitors to Headquarters, South Pacific Base Command, circa 1944-1945 (Box 62)
    Includes captions for each image
  - Groups of officers and soldiers in Oahu, 1944-1945 (Box 62)
  - Oahu and Saipan, 1944-1945 (Box 62)
    Mainly individuals and groups of military men
  - Iwo Jima, Tinian, and Palaus, 1944 (Box 62)
  - Okinawa, 1945 (Box 62)
  - Guam, 1944 (Box 62)
- Correspondence, 1941-1946 (Box 63-71)
  - Number 1 to 300, Personal, A-Z, A-B, 1941-1946 (Box 63)
  - Number 301 to 550, 1941-1946 (Box 64)
  - Number 551 to 800, 1941-1946 (Box 65)
  - Number 801 to 950, 1941-1946 (Box 66)
  - Number 951 to 1100, 1941-1946 (Box 67)
  - Number 1101 to 1300, 1941-1946 (Box 68)
  - Number 1301 to 1500, 1941-1946 (Box 69)
  - Number 1501 to 1800, 1941-1946 (Box 70)
  - Number 1801 to 2201, 1941-1946 (Box 71)
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1943-1946 (Box 73-74)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some interfield records determined by the government to be unclassified. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover.
  - 2015 May release of records, 1944 (Box 73)
    Correspondence, memoranda, and reports related to Saipan and Holland Smith/Ralph Smith, arranged chronologically. For related materials, see Box 35-36.
  - 2016 January release of records, 1943-1946 (Box 73-74)
    Correspondence, reports, memoranda, orders, and other communications related to Central Pacific Command and Richardson's role as Military Governor of Hawaii (specifically martial law and habeas corpus cases), arranged by original box number and folder title, then chronologically thereunder. The materials originally were in Boxes 12, 14, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 26, and 28.